你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎来到PWN学院 shellcoding模块的另一个视频
welcome to another video in the pwn college of shellcoding module
今天我们将讨论数据执行保护(DEP)
today we'll be talking about data execution Protection
简单地说一下
just very briefly
如果你还记得我们计算机架构基础中的3个John的话
if you remember the 3 Johns from our computer architecture fundamentals
他们给我们带来了冯·诺依曼架构
the 3 Johns gave us what is now called the John Von Neumann architecture
他们提出的这种架构基本上以相同的方式处理代码和数据
they proposed this architecture that basically treats code and data in the same way
好
right
它们都存储在内存中
they're all stored in memory
它们都会被读入CPU缓存，等等
they're all read into your CPU cache and so forth and so on
这就产生了问题
and this causes problems
正如我们前面在本模块中看到的
as we have seen throughout this module
这能让我们注入如同代码的数据
this allows us to inject data as if it were code
然后执行注入的代码
and have it executed
混乱随之而来
and chaos ensues
它在1988年摧毁了互联网
it brought down the internet in 1988
这是由于一个漏洞，它有涉及到shellcode
it you know as as an exploit that involved shellcode
它也导致你必须解决很多为你准备的有挑战性的作业题目
and it is caused you to have to tackle a lot of challenge problems that be prepared for you
这是这个设计决策的一个非常有趣的副作用
it's a pretty interesting side effect of this design decision
所以有时
so sometime
最近
relatively recently
在最近的可能差不多20年里
as in the last I don't know maybe almost 2 decades
计算机架构设计师开始考虑
computer architecture designers started thinking
如果我们对数据和代码的处理略有所不同呢
well what if we treat data and code slightly differently
就算有一点点不同呢？
right just a little bit
于是数据执行保护（DEP）就诞生了
and data execution Protection was born
现代架构支持对数据划分权限
modern architectures support permissions on data
这些权限可以是
these permissions can be
是否能读取这些数据
can we read this data
是否能写入（修改）这些数据
can we write this data
是否能执行这些数据
and can we execute this data
这些常量PROT_READ、 PROT_WRITE、 PROT_EXEC
so these constants PROT_READ PROT_WRITE PROT_EXEC
来自mmap和mprotect系统调用
are from you know the mmap and mprotect system calls
你可以使用它们
you can actually use them
定义映射内存的权限
to define the permissions of memory that you are mapping or
或者修改它的权限
changing the permissions of
这背后的原理是
the intuition behind this was
注意: 一般只有ELF中.text段的数据
look: normally all the data in your .text segment in your ELF
需要可执行权限
that's what needs to be executable
没人会执行
no one needs to execute
也不是没有，但通常栈上的数据不需要被执行
not no one but usually you don't need to execute the stack
有时确实会这样做，但这种情况很少
sometimes you do but that's rare
在这种情况下，你要自己想办法了
and in those cases you'll deal with it yourself
默认情况
right by default
我们要确保栈上数据不能执行
let's make sure nothing on the stack can be executed
程序代码不能更改
nothing in the program code can be changed
这样就相安无事了
everyone will be happy
不同的系统，对这种机制有不同的称呼
in different systems this is called different things
windows里它被称为DEP数据执行保护
on windows it tends to be called DEP data execution Protection
Linux系统里它经常被称为NX，即无执行位
on Linux systems that it is frequently referred to as NX the no execute bit
它也被称为W⊕X
it has been called or W⊕X
这很难写
this is very difficult to write
因为它包含了“⊕”
because it involves an ⊕
有时写成W+X
sometimes written as W+X
它传达的意思是
that conveys the idea that
执行权限和写权限不应该同时被赋予
something should never be executable and writeable at the same time
它有很多称呼，但总的来说
known by a lot of different things but generally speaking
DEP阻止了 shellcode或者说
Data Execute Protection prevent your shellcode
任何注入的数据的执行
any data that you inject from being able to execute
这终结了shellcode吗？
so is that the end of shellcode
好吧
well
它可能不会被毁灭
it might not be damned
但确实很受影响
but it definitely hurts
在某种程度上，shellcode现在是一种古老的艺术
shellcode in some way is now a little bit of an ancient art
只由神秘又聪明的黑客大佬使用
practiced by mysterious wise hackers
它在嵌入式设备中依旧非常普遍
it's still very very much around in embedded devices
仍然有很多嵌入式设备没有良好的DEP机制
there's still a lot of embedded devices that don't have good data execution Protection
在通用计算机领域，它也以不同方法存在着
and it is around in kind of the  general purpose computing landscape as well in a number of different ways
我们将在这节课中讨论
that we'll discuss in this lecture
我们讨论一下还能用的shellcode注入方法
let's talk about kind of the remaining data uh shellcode injection methods
首先
thing number one
最直接的说法就是
that the kind of most straightforward way to talk about is well
您可以使用系统调用
you can use a system call
mprotect系统调用
a system call called mprotect
来修改内存的权限
to actually change the permissions of memory
使其可执行
to make it executable
以及可写
and writeable right
这是一个先有鸡还是先有蛋的问题
this is kind of a chicken and egg problem
因为通常要能这样做
because usually in order to do that
你已经对程序有了一些高级别的控制
you already have to have some high level of control over a program
一个常见的方法是面向返回编程（ROP）
a very common way in hacking challenges to do it is through return oriented programming
将在以后的模块中讨论
which you will talk about in a future module
但基本上要创建一个面向返回的小程序
but you basically create a small return oriented program
用mprotect修改一小段内存的权限，然后
to mprotect a piece of memory and then
你通过它运行你的shellcode
you run your shellcode out of that
其他情况则非常看情况
other cases are very situational
这取决于程序的原有功能
it really depends on what is the program designed to do
有什么样的漏洞等等
what is the vulnerability and so forth
有些情况是可以绕过DEP的
it is not impossible to have this happen
特别是竞争条件之类的
especially as result of a race condition or something along these lines
但这要看情况
but it's a situational scenario
很多情况下shellcode仍然有用
a large class of scenarios were shellcode does still exist
它涉及到 JIT编译器
It involve just in time compilers
JIT编译器可以让你非常非常快地运行javascript
just in time compilers were created to allow you to run javascript very very very quickly
要注意的是解释型语言不只有js
right the idea is you take interpreted language it doesn't just have to be javascript
还可以是java字节码之类的
or you know java byte code or something along these lines
在运行时
and at runtime
为了能跑得更快，如果觉有必要
if you feel that it would help you run things faster
就编译那部分（能加快运行的）代码
you compile that a little bit of code at a time
后面正好可以运行它
just in time to to run it
just in Time编译有点超出了这门课的范围
just in Time compilation is a little bit outside of the scope of this course in general
如果你感兴趣，可以查一下
look it up if you are interested
网上有很多资源可以去了解它
there's you know a lot of resources on Internet to learn about it
但总的思想是会生成代码
but the general idea is you're generating code
会生成要被执行的二进制代码
you're generating binary code that needs to be able to run
所以生成的二进制代码需要能够
so that binary code that is generated needs to be able
写在某个地方，然后还要在那里执行
to be written somewhere and then executed from there
安全的做法是
right the safety thing to do
为它mmap一快内存，写入代码
would be to mmap a place just for it to write the code
然后用mprotect保护那块内存，这样那块内存
to then mprotect that place so that memory location
就不再是可写的了
so that it is no longer writeable
然后执行里面代码
then execute that code
如果需要更新它
if you need to update it
即时编译器通常是增量的
Just in time compilers are usually incremental
所以他们肯定会不断更新代码
so they'll have to update code over time
您需要再次调用mprotect使其可写
you'll need to once again mprotect it to be writeable
然后再调用mprotect使其只可执行
and then once again mprotect it to be executable only
这是最安全的做法
this is the safe thing to do
但是系统调用很慢
right but system calls are slow
所以这也是一件非常缓慢的事情
so there's also an extremely slow thing to do
事实上，像这样的方法可能会有巨大的开销
in fact an approach like this likely is going to have enormous overhead
而JIT编译的期望是要非常快的执行
and the point of just in time compilations should be very fast to
是为了加快速度
to speed things up
而安全会失去速度
and slow and safe tends to lose out over fast
因此，可写并可执行的内存页面是常见的
as a result writeable and executable pages are common
对，更糟的是
right and it's it gets a little worse even
如果你使用了库，而库使用了可写并可执行的内存页
if your program uses a library that uses writeable plus executable pages
这些内存页都在你的内存空间里
that those pages are in your memory space right
所以你也因此有了漏洞
so you're vulnerable too
让我来告诉你这些有多常见
but let me show you just how common these are
看看我能不能做到展示的同时不剧透
let's see if I can do this without spewing secrets all over the place
之前讲过/proc文件系统
talked about the slash proc file system before
在这里的/proc中，有机器上所有进程对应的目录
here in slash proc we have directories for all the processes running on machine
我们先用grep搜索一下这些进程
so let's just grep through all of these processes
这里有一个文件
there's a file
self表示当前进程
and for each of these process ID self is just symboling to my current
所以这就是ls的进程ID，这很酷
so this would be symboling to ls's process ID which is pretty cool
很灵活
all super dynamic and everything
好的，如果我们
all right if we
Grep查找所有进程maps中的RWX
grep all of these process maps for the word for the permissions rwx
好
right
理想情况下，我们一个也看不到，但我们看到了很多
ideally we wouldn't see any but we see a lot
看到了很多文件匹配这些权限
see a lot of files that match these permissions
我们可以用parallel来运行更多的命令
and we can use our friend parallel to run more commands here
如果我们
if we
让我们看看这是否可行
let's see if this works
嗯,让我们
uh let's
嗯好吧
yeah okay
让我们以基本名称/exe为例
let's just take the base name slash exe
所有这些程序都在内存中映射了一个可写且可执行的页面
all of these programs have a page mapped in memory that is writable and executable
这里有一些重量级人物
and there are some heavy hitters in here
X我的图形界面
X my freaking graphical interface
还有zoom
we have zoom
它也有一个可写可执行的页面
it has a writable and executable page
如果在zoom中有shellcode注入
if there is shellcode injection in zoom
这里就有一个地方可供shellcode执行
now there's a place for that shellcode execute from
Firefox！它里面有JIT编译器
Firefox has a just in time compiler
有可能RWX页面就在那里
it's possible it's there
我有点好奇
I'm actually curious
我不这么认为
I didn't think it was
很明显，这有点离题
obviously this is a little offscript
RWX在哪里
so where's the RWX
没找到
I don't see it
还是用聪明点的方法吧
well actually let's be smart about this
哦
oh
它在一个Nvidia库
it's an Nvidia library
由于某种原因，这个库映射了可写和可执行的页面
so here I mean for some reason this library has writable and executable page mapped
所以现在我的火狐浏览器也存在了
and as a result now my Firefox does as well
名单上还有谁
who else was on this list
一些GNOME组件、discord、slack
some GNOME components discord and slack
和obs
open broadcast system
我打赌这是因为它是电子应用程序
I bet this is because it's electron apps
不管怎样
anyways
甚至在我的系统上，都有可写和可执行的代码
a lot of things have writeable and executable code even on my system
甚至我的系统
even my system
好吧
all right
显然这让shellcode仍有用武之地
so obviously this could still allow some shellcode action
我们继续
let's move on
如果JIT是遵照安全方法实现的呢
what if the JIT was safe
在特定的情况下，你仍然可以攻击它
right well you can still attack it in given certain scenarios
有一种技术叫做JIT spray，想象一下
there's a technique called JIT spraying so imagine
JIT编译器需要编译你所有的代码
just in time compiler would need to compile all of your code
比如将所有javascript代码转换成二进制
that all of your javascript code for example into binary
如果你的javascript代码有一些常量
if your javascript code has Constants
它们恰好是有效的x86汇编指令的值
that happened to have the values of valid x86 assembly
它们可能被放在可执行的内存中
they might end up in memory that is executable
现在也有针对这个问题的缓解措施，但是
now there are mitigations that have been developed for this as well but
但概念仍然成立
but the general concepts still stand
你可能会
you could end up
你可能是一个恶意网站，可以在浏览器中运行自己的javascript
because you might be a malicious website that can run its own javascript in a browser
你可能使用JIT编译
you might be able to cause things to be just in time compiled
并将结果通过可控的方式存入内存
and placed into memory in ways that you more or less control
然后触发漏洞将代码重定向到那里
and then by triggering a vulnerability to redirect code to there
这样就在运行shellcode了
you're running shellcode
顺便说一下，这种情况也会发生
this also happens by the way
这不仅仅是一个理论问题
all right and JIT isn't just a theoretical problem right
JIT无处不在
JIT is everywhere
它在你的浏览器中
it's in your browser
在你们很多人使用的软件中都有
it's in a lot of you know software that you're using
它肯定在javascript解释器中
it's in your javascript interpreter for sure
在你的lua解释器中
in your lua interpreter
在你的python解释器中，如果你使用pypy等
in your python interpreter if you're using pypy etc
它非常有用
a very useful thing
但它重新打开了这个攻击向量
but it reopens this attack vector
另一个保护机制是
another mitigation
只是预览一下，因为下一讲你们会讲到这个
just a preview  because you're gonna move on to this in the next module
如果
what happens if we say okay fine
攻击者会以某种方式运行他们的shellcode
the attacker is gonna run their shellcode somehow
我们能够避免shellcode造成很大的伤害吗
but can we prevent that shellcode from doing a lot of damage
请继续关注
stay tuned